<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-11-16T05:57:41+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Dean Robinson</title><subtitle>My Portfolio and Blog</subtitle><author><name>Dean Robinson</name></author><entry><title type="html">Creating my New Blog!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/My-New-Blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creating my New Blog!" /><published>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/My-New-Blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/My-New-Blog/">&lt;p&gt;Blog post about creating this blog&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dean Robinson</name></author><category term="Blog" /><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="GitHub" /><category term="Web Design" /><summary type="html">Blog post about creating this blog</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lost in spaCy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Lost-in-spaCy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lost in spaCy" /><published>2021-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Lost-in-spaCy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Lost-in-spaCy/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In spaCy no one can hear you scream… &lt;br /&gt;when you get a Syntax error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experiments with spaCy are going well in the appropriately named Jupyter notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two spaCy Natural Language Processing (NLP) components I am working with 1) Position of Speech (POS) and 2) Named Entity Recognition&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tutorial was really helpful in generalising the experiments I have been doing and looking at different aspects and capabilities of NLP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea with this is to get a general set of tools developed in a notebook before looking at adapting the code to be used in Power BI to run NLP as a step in Power Query.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big question is if you can load the NLP language library into Python running in Power BI (if not it is going to be tricky).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;starting-point&quot;&gt;Starting Point&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I am starting from an example here where NLP tools have been used to get an overview count of the contents of a csv of text values - which is great - but not what I need for a Power BI report to be able to explore the context of the results further so the following is simplified to just return the results of the NLP steps per result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the following I am assuming that you know the basics of installing modules and have done some introductory Python stuff all of which is very widely available online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The files and code is all available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/drdataanalysis/blog_python-text-analysis&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dean Robinson</name></author><category term="Blog" /><category term="Python" /><summary type="html">Post covering getting started with spaCy in Python for Natural Language Processing (NLP)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Starting Py-Fun!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/Starting-PyFun/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starting Py-Fun!" /><published>2021-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/Starting-PyFun</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/Starting-PyFun/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;-the-idea&quot;&gt;💡 The Idea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I wanted a way to document and encourage practicing of my experiments with Python and integrating it with Azure ML, Power BI which is a major project I am currently working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;-the-plan&quot;&gt;📋 The Plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to blog as regularly as possible covering the Python exploration and investigation that I am doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan is to help document the challenges and experience of trying to work to bring Python into the Microsoft Power Platform and processes that are used in my team. This area is something that I have not found many resources about in my work so far so I am conscious that some of this may be of help to others which is another reason to put this into a blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;-next-steps&quot;&gt;👣 Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Publish this post&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start looking at Natural Language Processing in Python (using Jupyter notebooks)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Convert Jupyter code to Power BI for use in data models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Dean Robinson</name></author><category term="Blog" /><category term="Python" /><summary type="html">Intro to the blog and the work that I am planning to do with Python</summary></entry></feed>